<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Finished | Littorina Lab</title>
    <link>/en/tags/finished/</link>
      <atom:link href="/en/tags/finished/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Finished</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>© Littorina Lab 2018-2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Finished</title>
      <link>/en/tags/finished/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular and morphological variation in sister species of Littorina</title>
      <link>/en/project/rfbr-2015-molecular-evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/project/rfbr-2015-molecular-evolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;molecular-evolution-of-closely-related-marine-intertidal-gastropods-from-proteomes-to-localization-of-genes-on-chromosomes&#34;&gt;Molecular evolution of closely related marine intertidal gastropods: from proteomes to localization of genes on chromosomes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RFBR #15-04-08210&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EMAP</title>
      <link>/en/project/rfbr-2014-emap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/project/rfbr-2014-emap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;environmental-management-of-petroleum-activities-in-the-barents-sea-norwegian-russian-collaboration-emap&#34;&gt;Environmental MAnagement of Petroleum activities in the Barents Sea: Norwegian-Russian collaboration (EMAP)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RFBR # 14-04-93083&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Arctic region is increasingly involved in oil and gas production, the importance of developing common approaches to environmental monitoring is growing. This is especially important for areas of the Barents Sea, where international consortia are developing Norwegian and Russian oil reserves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We propose taking advantage of the existing cooperation of science and industry in the field of environmental monitoring in the Norwegian sector, as well as the proven history of bilateral interactions of environmental management and environmental expertise between Russia and Norway. In accordance with this, the goal of the proposed project is the development of unified, based on a unified methodology, standards for environmental monitoring of oil production regions, which will significantly improve coordination of efforts of the two countries in applied and basic research of the Arctic region and will make possible a wide exchange of expert assessments between Russian and Norwegian research groups. Leading institutions &amp;mdash; the project participants with significant experience in cooperation among each other &amp;mdash; will use the opportunities offered by the project to work together to build a common database in three blocks of environmental monitoring of the Arctic shelf: distribution of benthic communities, the impact of pollutants on marine organisms and the geochemistry of hydrocarbons. The taxonomic approach to description of the key faunal groups will be unified, existing biotic indices will be tested to evaluate the potential effect of pollutants on biocenoses. The latest biosensor technologies will be tested to determine pollution thresholds on model species of marine fauna. A general database of hydrocarbon concentration will be created, allowing the use of available methods to analyse distribution and composition of polyaromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) to draw conclusions about the exogenous or endogenous origin of PAHs and the corresponding conclusions about the source of pollution. These efforts, reinforced by efforts to develop joint educational programs within existing related projects, will further strengthen institutional and scientific cooperation that will go far beyond the objectives of this project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
