<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Current | Littorina Lab</title>
    <link>/en/tags/current/</link>
      <atom:link href="/en/tags/current/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Current</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>© Littorina Lab 2018-2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Current</title>
      <link>/en/tags/current/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallel speciation in littorines</title>
      <link>/en/project/rsf-2019-parallel-speciation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/project/rsf-2019-parallel-speciation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ecological-and-molecular-backgroung-of-speciation-the-model-of-parallel-speciation-in-the-complex-of-cryptic-species-of-intertidal-molluscs&#34;&gt;Ecological and molecular backgroung of speciation: the model of parallel speciation in the complex of cryptic species of intertidal molluscs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RSF #19-14-00321&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is devoted to the analysis of processes of intraspecific divergence, the formation of distinct intraspecific groups in the scope of the feasibility of the parallel, unidirectional morphological and functional changes of the groups of individuals in different parts of the species range, in locations with similar gradients of environmental factors (parallel &amp;ldquo;race formation&amp;rdquo;). The proof of this phenomenon raises an even more important question about the possibility of a parallel, independent formation of similar groups of species rank, repeated at different parts of the species range. This model of speciation is an alternative to the model, which recognizes unique, single and highly stochastic speciation followed by dispersal (young species range formation) and the formation of zones of secondary contact with the populations of the ancestral species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the framework of the formulated fundamental problem, we offer, on the one hand, to demonstrate the repetitive acts of differentiation of populations of species in ecological gradients at the level of the phenotype and genotype in different geographical regions, and on the other hand, to verify the possibility of independent divergence of the young cryptic species in the same geographic locations on basis of the same genetic data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The selected model system - two groups of cryptic species of the genus Littorina subgenus Neritrema (Mollusca: Caenogastropoda: Littorinidae) - &amp;ldquo;saxatilis&amp;rdquo; (L.arcana, L.compressa, L.saxatilis) and &amp;ldquo;obtusata&amp;rdquo; (L.fabalis, L.obtusata), which form sympatric populations, and whose environmental preferences overlap to varying degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project&#39;s objective is to carry out comprehensive comparisons within the two categories of objects: (1) intraspecific ecological groups within each of the three species from &amp;ldquo;saxatilis&amp;rdquo; group (a natural model of the situation &amp;ldquo;before the speciation&amp;rdquo;); (2) young species (respectively, interspecies analysis of all five of these species, the natural model of the situation &amp;ldquo;after the speciation&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We plan to perform a comprehensive comparative analysis of eight populations of each species from 4 geographically distant regions (2 populations from each region - the British Isles, the Atlantic Coast (1); Breton peninsula, the Channel (2); The northern part of the Scandinavian Peninsula, the Norwegian Sea (3); Kola peninsula, the Barents sea (4)). For each of the analyzed categories we will obtain a complex description phenotype of individuals at the morphological (morphometric analysis of shell) and molecular levels (profiles of proteins expressed and metabolites produced), description of environmental preferences (distribution in the intertidal zone, the food spectrum), and genotyping based on restriction-site associated DNA markers (RADseq-tags).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total, such a multilevel analysis will show the formation of parallel rows of variability in different populations of different species at the level of phenotype; genetic analysis will reveal adaptively significant loci and assess whether their composition is similar across species. In addition, it will provide an opportunity to understand how likely is the independent divergence of young species within the cryptic groups at each location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project will be carried out using the equipment of the St. Petersburg State University resource centers &amp;ldquo;Centre for Molecular and Cell Technologies&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Environmental Safety Observatory&amp;rdquo;. Completion of the project will allow to determine the molecular mechanisms of formation of a complex of closely related species and ecological intraspecific morphs. The new data will be important for understanding of the overall process of speciation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Host-parasite co-speciation</title>
      <link>/en/project/rfbr-2019-host-parasite-cospeciation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/project/rfbr-2019-host-parasite-cospeciation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;local-evolutionary-adaptations-and-host-parasite-interactions-multilevel-analysis-of-closely-related-gastropod-species&#34;&gt;Local evolutionary adaptations and host-parasite interactions: multilevel analysis of closely related gastropod species&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RFBR #19-04-00392&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biological adaptation is a key process concerning such important scientific areas as organism homeostasis, interactions with environment, speciation, etc. This determines the importance of studies of adaptations and its mechanisms. This project is devoted to analysis of how organisms living in heterogenic environment make their adaption to biotopes occupied. Intertidal snails of the genus Littorina were chosen as a model system. Metabolomics and proteomics as principal approaches will be used for characterizing physiological features of animals collected from wild populations. We will analyze effects of abiotic factors on organisms&amp;rsquo; physiology in dependence on species, intertidal level, trematode infection and gut microsymbionts composition in example of snails; similar analysis of population partitioning will be performed for trematode parasites. So, within one project proteomics, metabolomics, molecular marker analysis, metagenomic analysis of gut microbiome, parasitology and population ecology will be jointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to reveal molecular mechanisms of local adaptations on the basis of metabolomic and proteomic profiles analysis in the context of population ecology (intraspecies level) and evolution (interspecies level in the group of closely related species). The effect of trematode parasites on host adaptability and physiology will also be estimated. The relevance of the projects proposed is determined by contribution of expected results to several fundamental biological problems, such as, molecular mechanisms of adaptation; intraspecies plasticity of these mechanisms and its reasons; speciation mechanisms; host-parasite interactions. Such a multifaceted approach puts the proposed project onto current edge of ecological and evolutionary biology and makes the expected results of high demand.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EcoSens</title>
      <link>/en/project/rfbr-2018-ecosens/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/project/rfbr-2018-ecosens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;environmental-monitoring-of-arctic-coastal-ecosystems-sensitivity-to-petroleum-pollution-arctic-ecosens&#34;&gt;Environmental monitoring of Arctic coastal ecosystems: Sensitivity to petroleum pollution (Arctic EcoSens)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RFBR #18-54-20001&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state of Arctic biocenoses reflects global dynamic processes associated with climate change and, at the same time, reflects local anthropogenic impact. In the Arctic, the rapid expansion of human economic activity  such as oil and gas production is one of significant factors, which impact on natural communities requires a thorough assessment. In addition to practical significance, this situation also provides an opportunity to model biota dynamics in changing environmental conditions. In this regard, the main fundamental component of the project is the assessment of the degree of stability of Arctic biocenoses, the analysis of the mechanisms that ensure it in the gradient of environmental conditions, and development of new approaches for monitoring of Arctic biocenoses.&lt;/p&gt;








  
  


&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
  

  
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-ecosens&#34; data-caption=&#34;Photo: Arina Maltseva&#34; href=&#34;/img/ecosens/DSCN3979.JPG&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/ecosens/DSCN3979.JPG&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-ecosens&#34; data-caption=&#34;Photo: Arina Maltseva&#34; href=&#34;/img/ecosens/DSCN4320.JPG&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img data-src=&#34;/img/ecosens/DSCN4320.JPG&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
  
  
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fullfill the project&#39;s goals, it is important that the structure of the complex &amp;ldquo;pollution effect&amp;rdquo; can be quantified as the ratio of the components of polyaromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) of biogenic, petrogenic and pyrogenic origin (a “fingerprint” passport of PAH pollution at each site studied), and measuring the concentration of heavy metals (working package (WP) 1). This makes it possible to assess the correlation of the “pollution effect” with the structural biocenotic parameters of the model intertidal communities of salt marches and rocky intertidal sites (WP). Moreover, the use of experimental methods such as proteomics and metabolics to assess modell communities allows us to draw conclusions about the effect of factors and the state of biota (WP 3). The main objective of the project is to assess the impact of factors associated with oil and gas production and associated anthropogenic activity in the polar region on model biocenoses using modern geochemical, synecological and autecological approaches, modernization of the methodology for monitoring biocenoses of the Barents Sea at oil production sites, and exchange of experience between Russian and Norwegian research institutes and universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project uses the strong side of decades-long scientific cooperation between Russia and Norway, which involves environmental monitoring of the Barents Sea, development of environmental impact standards for both countries.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
